Hybrbridge, a division of recorded
books, presents
Doing Time Like a Spy: How the CIA
Taught Me to Survive and Thrive in
Prison by John Kuryaku.
Read by Jonathan Yen.
Every current and former CIA officer
must submit his book manuscript to the
CIA's notorious and politicized
publications review board PRB for
clearance to ensure that the book does
not contain classified information.
Well, every current and former CIA
officer is supposed to submit the
manuscript. Many don't. The ones who are
famous or are friends with the president
get away with it. The little guy who
doesn't ends up getting crushed in a
court of law.
I submitted my manuscript and despite
the fact that the federal courts have
mandated that the CIA has 30 days to
review it, my book took more than 8
months.
Still, I played by the rules, even if
the CIA didn't. In the end, the CIA
necessitated the following disclaimer.
This does not constitute an official
release of CIA information. All
statements of fact, opinion, or analysis
expressed are those of the author and do
not reflect the official positions or
views of the Central Intelligence
Agency. CIA or any other US government
agency. Nothing in the contents should
be construed as asserting or implying US
government authentication of information
or CIA endorsement of the author's
views. This material has been reviewed
solely for classification.
Introduction.
I like to think that I'm a pretty nice
guy. In fact, people tell me all the
time that I'm friendly, and easy to get
along with. I consider myself a good
father, a good husband, a hard worker,
and a patriot.
But in prison, I had a reputation for
being an [__] I was comfortable in
prison plotting against people, cutting
off those who crossed me, and trying
constantly to stay one step ahead of the
corrections officers, CEOs, and the
prison administration.
I am an experienced, highly trained
former CIA operations officer. It was my
job to recruit spies to steal secrets
and to run counterterrorist operations,
to break up and foil terrorist plots.
I'm very proud of my CIA career. I spent
nearly 15 years there and I played a
role in the country's response to the
September 11th, 2001 attacks.
I spent the first eight years of my CIA
career working in analysis and
specializing on Iraq. My final seven
years were spent on the ground in
counterterrorism.
I resigned from the CIA in 2004.
Despite my career, which included a
later stint as the senior investigator
for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee, and nearly a half ccentury of
being a law-abiding citizen, I
eventually found myself as the target of
a federal investigation.
At the end of the ordeal, I was
sentenced to 30 months in prison. I was
determined to get through my prison
experience unscathed, and I thought the
best way to do that would be to rely on
what the CIA had taught me over the
years. After all, prison couldn't
possibly be tougher than Afghanistan,
Pakistan, Iraq, Yemen, or any of the
other dumps in which I'd served over the
years. I resolved to make the best of a
bad situation, to stay safe, and to make
sure that I remained at the top of the
social heap.
When I came to prison, I didn't know
what to expect. Nobody among my friends
had ever been to prison, and I had
nothing to go on other than what I had
seen on TV. What I did not expect,
however, was that the training and
experience that I had amassed in my CIA
career would prepare me to survive and
thrive in prison. As you will see, I
wasn't the typical federal prisoner.
A CIA psychiatrist once told me that the
agency looks to hire people who exhibit
sociopathic tendencies.
CIA recruiters are not interested in
sociopaths who have no consciences or
empathy and who can easily pass a
polygraph exam. Sociopaths are too hard
to control.
Instead, they are interested in people
who are comfortable working in ethical,
moral, and legal gray areas. I had no
problem bending some rules if it was in
the interest of national security.
Some researchers have gone further in
their analysis of the typical CIA
officer than the CIA psychiatrist who
told me about sociopathic tendencies.
New Mexico State University professor
Peter Jonison published a paper entitled
Who is James Bond? Which found that
successful intelligence officers have a
specific triumvirant of personality
traits? the stratospheric self-esteem of
narcissism, the fearlessness,
ruthlessness, impulsivity, and
thrillseeking of psychopathy, and the
deceitfulness and exploitiveness of
Machavevelianism.
That's a little harsh. An actual
psychopath or sociopath, according to
Dutton, seeks reward at any cost,
flouting consequence and elbowing risk
aside.
That's not at all what a CIA officer
does. He tries to get the job done while
not making waves or attracting undue
attention.
That's exactly what I did in prison.
The CIA recruited me in graduate school
in the late 1980s for a reason. I was
and remain very patriotic and I was very
interested in public service. I also had
a bachelor's degree in Middle Eastern
studies and a master's degree in
legislative affairs as well as a
facility for foreign languages. A
retired CIA officer teaching at my alma
mater, George Washington University,
spotted me, made a few introductions,
and after a battery of tests and a
comprehensive background investigation,
I found myself at CIA headquarters in
Langley, Virginia.
I'm glad I joined the CIA. The CIA
taught me great survival skills. I'm not
just talking about how to break into
houses, how to surreptitiously gather
information, or even how to use weapons
in dangerous situations.
I'm talking about how to survive and
even thrive when surrounded by idiots,
dangerous criminals, crooked cops,
corrupt administrators, sexual perverts,
and the scum of society.
You see, this is prison.
How could this happen?
I began working at the CIA in January
1990. After a week of orientation, I was
assigned to an office in the Directorate
of Intelligence, DI, the AY's analytic
arm that focused on doing long-term
psychological profiles of foreign
leaders.
My assignment was to cover Iraq and
Kuwait, which I was told were training
accounts. As a senior analyst explained
to me, nothing ever happens in Iraq or
Kuwait. They've had the same leadership
since the 1960s.
The same cabinets are still in place.
Learn your analytic trade craft and you
can move on to something interesting
like Romania.
That was 8 months before Iraq invaded
Kuwait and started the Gulf War.
The Gulf War made me a star in the DI. I
became one of the AY's goto analysts on
Iraq. I was Saddam Hussein's biographer
for the intelligence community and I was
called on to brief presidents, cabinet
secretaries, members of Congress, and
foreign leaders. I traveled to more than
60 countries and wrote analyses that
helped to form the basis for US policy
in the Middle East. But I got bored. By
1997, it was clear that Saddam Hussein
wasn't going anywhere. I wanted to go
back overseas where I had served in the
early 1990s. I spoke both Greek and
Arabic, which was unique in the agency,
and I decided that I wanted to switch to
counterterrorism operations.
A move from analysis to operations was
highly unusual at the time. There was
normally a Chinese wall between the
CIA's two most important functions, but
the counterterrorism center thought that
I showed promise, and my language skills
were unique, and they allowed me to make
the switch.
I didn't have to do interim one-month
assignments around headquarters, what
people call CIA 101, because my
colleagues and I in the special
operations training course, SOTC, were
all mid-career officers. Instead, I dove
right into operations. First at a secret
facility in Northern Virginia and then
in the CIA's famous training facility
known as the farm.
SOTC was a deep, involved, and difficult
course. It was also the most fun I've
ever had. Besides learning the
fundamentals of operational writing,
clandestine meetings, disguises, and
other espionage basics, there were other
components. These included crash and
bang, a course on how to avoid
kidnappings and carborne terrorist
attacks, weapons training with a variety
of handguns, long guns, and even some
heavy weaponry, surveillance, counter
surveillance, and surveillance
detection, and parachute jump school.
But it was the other courses that I
really took, too. The most interesting
and professionally important one was how
to spot, assess, develop, and recruit
spies.
Unless you plan to make your career as
an ass kicker in places like
Afghanistan, Iraq, or Pakistan,
recruitment skills would be the most
valuable for a career in CIA operations.
These skills proved to be the most
valuable to me in prison.
Operational meetings could be held
anywhere. In a restaurant, in a hotel,
in a car, literally anywhere. I've even
done operational meetings in a men's
restroom, and behind a garbage dumpster.
The idea at first is to spot a target
and to assess his access to protected
information. Once you find the right
person, you cultivate and develop a
friendship so that over time the target
becomes more and more comfortable
speaking openly with you. The final
phase in the relationship is
recruitment. Here you establish a formal
relationship between the CIA and the
target. There are lots of reasons people
would consent to being recruited. These
are called vulnerabilities.
Maybe the target needs money. He can't
afford his lifestyle. He can't afford to
send his kids to college or he has large
medical bills. Revenge is a good
motivator. Maybe the target has been
passed over for promotion or has a beef
against his bosses.
Another motivator may be patriotism. The
target loves the US and wants to help.
Whatever the motivation though, every
recruitment comes down to the
relationship.
In this kind of clandestine
relationship, trust and a personal
connection are paramount. After all, the
goal is to convince someone to commit
espionage, treason even for you. Why?
Because he likes you. He believes he can
work with you and he gets something that
he needs out of the relationship. money,
revenge, even just a shoulder to cry on.
This is the very foundation of CIA
operational work.
I had no idea at the time, of course,
but it was these skills that would allow
me to protect myself and my interests in
prison. I learned in my CIA training
that almost everybody has a
vulnerability. Almost everybody or every
situation can be manipulated. I honed
these skills in the Middle East and
Europe virtually as soon as I finished
training.
I had to live by my wits while serving
overseas.
There were two assassination attempts
made against me abroad. one in Greece
where a terrorist group called
Revolutionary Organization 17 November
set out to kill me but murdered my
neighbor, the British Defense Ataché,
instead. The second was in a Middle
Eastern country where I was handling a
double agent. The enemy country he was
working for ordered him to kill me in
our final meeting. We were tipped off.
We grabbed and disarmed him and we
cracked his organization.
Then the September 11th attacks
occurred. Like everybody else at CIA
headquarters, I volunteered to go to
Afghanistan and fight. That wasn't
really my thing. I have no military
experience, but patriotism dictated that
I do my part. I volunteered repeatedly,
and finally, after making enough of a
pest of myself, I was sent to Pakistan
to run counterterrorist operations. I
spent most of 2002 there.
The highlight of my time in Pakistan was
the late March 2002 capture of Abu Zuba
and dozens of al-Qaeda fighters at a
string of safe houses in Fisal Ababad.
This was a major catch. Our government
thought at the time that Abu Zubeda was
the third ranking official in Alqaeda,
but that turned out to be untrue. While
Abu Zabeda had certainly done a lot of
logistical work for Al-Qaeda, and he
created and ran the group's training
camps in southern Afghanistan, he had
never actually joined al-Qaeda. He had
never pledged loyalty to Osama bin
Laden, and he knew less about al-Qaeda's
leadership than we thought he did.
I didn't have any idea at the time how
important Abu Zubeda would be to my life
over the next decade. Frankly, I wish I
had never been in Pakistan that night.
You can keep the medals and awards. In
the end, as you'll see, it wasn't worth
it to me.
When I got back to CIA headquarters in
the summer of 2002, a senior officer in
the AY's counterterrorism center asked
me if I wanted to be certified in the
use of what he called enhanced
interrogation techniques. I didn't know
what that meant, so I asked. He told me,
"We're going to start getting rough with
these guys." and he explained the
various torture techniques that had
recently been approved by President
George W. Bush. I told this officer that
this sounds like torture to me. And I
said that I had a visceral opposition to
it. Count me out.
But just to make sure I was thinking
correctly, I went to a very senior CIA
officer and asked for his guidance. He
said, "First, let's call it what it is.
It's torture. Second, somebody is going
to go too far and they're going to kill
a prisoner. Third, there's going to be a
congressional investigation and
somebody's going to go to prison. Do you
want to go to prison?" I said, "No." and
I went back to the counterterrorism
center and said in no uncertain terms
that I didn't want to be involved.
In the end, I was the only person with
any connection to the CIA's torture
program that went to prison. Not because
I tortured anybody, but because I blew
the whistle on the CIA's torture
program. I aired the AY's dirty laundry
in public.
On August 1st, 2002, CIA interrogators
began torturing Abu Zubeda. At first, he
was slapped, punched, kicked, stripped
naked, and humiliated.
Later, he was chained to an eyebolt in
the ceiling and kept awake for weeks at
a time while ice water was thrown on
him. Abu Zuba exhibited an irrational
fear of insects. So he was put in a dog
cage with cockroaches to see how crazy
he could become.
Most famously or infamously, he was
waterboarded 83 times.
The Senate Select Committee on
Intelligence said in its torture report
in 2014
that none of these techniques resulted
in Abu Zuba ever giving the CIA any
actionable intelligence that disrupted
terrorist attacks or saved a single
American life.
While all of this was going on, CIA
officers speaking out of school were
telling me and others that Abu Zubeda
had been waterboarded once, that he had
cracked, and that he had provided
actionable intelligence that foiled
terrorist plots and saved lives.
This was a lie, but it was what was
being circulated around CIA
headquarters. It was a lie that helped
to perpetuate the torture program.
I resigned from the CIA in 2004.
I was divorced and I had remarried this
time to a CIA officer and I wanted to be
able to spend quality time with my two
sons from my first marriage. I was tired
of going overseas and my boys were young
at the time, 11 and 8. They needed me in
their lives and I needed them. So I left
the CIA and went into the private
sector.
Things were going gang busters for me
until December 2007.
At the beginning of that month, I
received a call from Brian Ross, the
senior investigative reporter for ABC
News. Ross said that he had a source who
had told him that I had tortured Abu
Zubeda.
Absolutely untrue, I said. I was the
only person who was kind to Abu Zuba.
Indeed, after we had captured him, I sat
at Abu Zubeta's side for 56 consecutive
hours. We talked about religion, poetry,
our families, even the September 11th
attacks.
At one point, in tears, he asked me to
smother him with his pillow.
I told Ross that his source was dead
wrong.
Well, you're welcome to come on the show
and defend yourself," he answered. I had
no idea that this was an old reporter's
trick. I should have hung up on him.
Instead, I went to my boss and my boss's
boss and asked what to do. "Go on the
show, but don't mention the firm or any
of the firm's clients," was the answer.
So, I went on the show.
I had honestly stopped following news
about al-Qaeda after I left the CIA. I
was burned out and I was excited to
start a new life. I was vaguely aware
that the non-governmental organization
Human Rights Watch had issued a report
saying that Abu Zubeda had been tortured
and that Amnesty International had
issued a report saying the same thing.
So, in my mind, the news was out there.
Everybody knew we were torturing
prisoners, right? Wrong. Brian Ross
asked me directly during the course of
the interview whether the CIA had
tortured Abu Zuba. Yes, I said. Was he
waterboarded? Yes. Were others? Yes. I
told the whole story.
Ross went on to ask me for my own
feelings about waterboarding.
I said that I thought it was torture and
that as Americans, we shouldn't be in
the business of torture. I made three
major revelations during that interview.
I said the CIA was torturing its
prisoners, that torture was official US
government policy, and that the policy
had been approved personally by the
president. By saying that, I became the
first CIA officer, past or present, to
confirm the torture of prisoners.
The CIA was enraged.
The next morning, the CIA filed a crimes
report against me with the FBI, saying
that my revelations were illegal and
asking the FBI to begin a criminal
investigation.
I read about this filing in the
newspapers and I hired an attorney.
The FBI took a full year to investigate
me. In the end, they elected not to
charge me with a crime, finding that I
had not revealed any classified
information. The case against me was
officially closed.
But the CIA was livid. Four weeks after
the case was closed, Barack Obama, the
self-professed most transparent
president in history, was inaugurated.
The CIA asked him secretly to reopen the
case against me. He did, and the secret
investigation proceeded for another four
years.
I didn't know it at the time, of course,
but the FBI was all over me, carrying
out surveillance against me, collecting
my telephone metadata, even intercepting
and reading my emails.
Again, I didn't know it at the time, so
I just continued on with my life.
Despite having my boss's permission to
go on ABC in 2007, I was asked to resign
from the private company I was working
for. I hired another attorney, and after
the provision of a generous severance
package, I offered my resignation.
Still, the timing could not have been
worse. I left my job just as the worst
recession since the Great Depression hit
the country. I was out of work for all
of 2008 other than a little consulting
work here and there until finally in
February 2009 I got an offer.
A friend with ties to then senator John
Kerry offered me a job as the senior
investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee staff. It was a
senior position on the most prestigious
committee on Capitol Hill and I was
thrilled at the prospect. I just had to
get through an interview with Carrie,
who had just been elevated to the
committee's chairmanship.
I met with Carrie in his office in
February 2009.
I was immediately struck by his
friendliness and informality.
Carrie gets a bum rap for his reputation
as a stiff patrician politician. I liked
him. He was very intelligent,
accomplished, and a bonafide war hero. I
was struck by a couple of things during
that meeting. First, he had his medals,
a silver star and three bronze stars in
a shadow box on a credenza. The press
had reported in great detail in the
1970s that Carrie had thrown his medals
over the White House fence to protest
the Vietnam War. That was a publicity
stunt. He threw copies over the fence
and kept the originals.
He also had pictures of himself with
John Lennon, Mary Travers of Peter, Paul
and Mary, and a wide variety of 1960s
and 1970s era celebrities. It was a fun
office.
Carrie and I had a great conversation
about the Middle East and South Asia. He
asked my opinion on the Iraq War, on the
occupation of Afghanistan, and on
strategies for getting out of both of
those countries. The interview went
exceedingly well. At the end, I got up
and shook his hand and I thanked him for
not asking me about waterboarding.
I hate being the water boarding guy, I
told him. Carrie smiled and said,
"Nobody in this country has taken it on
the chin from the press like I have. I
know the truth of your story. I'm happy
to have you on board."
I started working two weeks later.
I was blessed with great leadership for
the first year of my stint at the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. We tackled
some important issues, and I took very
seriously our oversight
responsibilities.
I thought that hard work and tough
investigations were what was expected of
me. I was wrong, wrong, wrong. And all I
did was stir up a hornets's nest of
troubles.
I didn't realize it at the time, but
even before I joined the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee staff, I was
ruffling feathers at Langley.
First, before I joined the SFRC, I had
written an op-ed for the Los Angeles
Times saying that the next president,
whether it was Barack Obama or John
McCain, should work to improve US
relations with South America because
Iran already was doing that. I sent it
to the CIA's publications review board,
PRB, for clearance before submitting it
to the Times, and it was cleared
quickly. My sources for the piece were
two reports from United Press
International's Spanish Language Service
and the Foreign Ministry website of one
of the countries I mentioned in the
piece.
A couple of days after the op-ed ran, my
wife was called into the CIA's Office of
Security as part of an inquiry. The
officer who videotaped the interview
said, "I noticed that your husband had
an op-ed run in the LA Times over the
weekend." My wife responded that I had
had the op-ed cleared. "Well," the
officer continued, "that Oped contained
highly classified information."
My wife answered calmly that I did not
have access to classified information.
But you do, the officer retorted.
My wife and I had a hard and fast rule
at home. We never talked about Iran,
ever.
The officer told her that we could
dispense with the entire episode if she
would fax him my sources. I emailed them
to her immediately and told her to.
>> Sample complete. Ready to continue.